Eugenie Gershoy
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Eugenie Gershoy papers
1914-1983
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Eugenie Gershoy
7.2 linear feet
The papers of sculptor and art instructor, Eugenie Gershoy, measure 7.2 linear feet and date from 1914 to 1983. The collection documents Gershoy's career through biographical material, correspondence, business records, notes, writings, artwork, printed material, and photographs.
Biographical Note
Born in Krivoi Rog, Russia on January 1, 1901, Eugenie was the youngest of the Gershoy children. The family immigrated to New York City in 1903. She later became a U.S. citizen.
With the aid of two scholarships, she attended the Art Students League and studied under A. Stirling Calder, Leo Lentelli, Kenneth Hayes Miller, Boardman Robinson, and Carl Walters. During the late 1920s and early 1930s, she maintained a studio with Harry Gottlieb in Woodstock, New York. From 1936 to 1939, under the WPA Federal Art Project, she worked in conjunction with Max Spivak on murals for the children's recreation room in the Astoria branch of the Queens Borough Public Library, New York.
Gershoy's first solo show was at the Robinson Gallery in New York in 1940. Following a year of teaching at the New Orleans Art School, she moved to San Francisco in 1942. In 1946 she taught ceramics at the California School of Fine Arts, and in May 1950, she studied at Yaddo.
In addition to visits to England and France in the early 1930s, Gershoy travelled to Mexico and Guatemala in 1947, 1948, and 1961. She worked in Paris in 1951 and toured Africa, India, and the Orient in 1955.
Eugenie Gershoy died in 1986.
Scope and Content Note
The Eugenie Gershoy papers date from 1914 to 1983, measure 7.2 linear feet, and reflect Gershoy's career as a sculptor and teacher. The collection contains biographical material, correspondence, business records, notes, writings, artwork of Gershoy and others, printed material including exhibition catalogs, and photographs with subjects including Gershoy, her friends and colleagues, her studio, and her artwork.
Correspondence forms the bulk of the collection and includes correspondence between Gershoy and her siblings and their families regarding her activities, as well as with colleagues, many of whom were associated with the Woodstock Artist Association, and many of whom were museum colleagues.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into eight series according to material type. The contents of each series have been arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1939-1971 (boxes 1 and 9, sol 8, 2 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1914-1983, undated (boxes 1-6, 9, sol 8, 5.8 linear ft.)
Series 3: Business Records, 1952-1978 (box 6, 5 folders)
Series 4: Notes, 1967-1970, undated (box 6, 3 folders)
Series 5: Writings, 1970, undated (box 6, 2 folders)
Series 6: Artwork, 1932-1978, undated (boxes 6, 8-9, OV 10, 26 folders)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1932-1983, undated (boxes 7 and 9, 19 folders)
Series 8: Photographs, 1916-1983, undated (boxes 7 and 9, 12 folders)
Related Material
Related material in the Archives of American Art includes a transcribed oral history interview with Eugenie Gershoy conducted by Mary McChesney for the Archives of American Art's New Deal and the Arts Oral History Program, October 15, 1964. A link to the transcript is provided from the online catalog.
Appendix: Notable Correspondents from Series 2 - Correspondence
Art Students League: see Photographs
Avery, Frances: undated Christmas cards (2); 1967 Christmas card
Baber, Alice: Oct 16, 1975; Oct 21, 1975
Baker, Mildred: undated letters (20); May 22, 1969; [Aug 1971]; May 25, 1980; Mar 10, 1981; Mar 17, 1981; Mar 26, 1981; Jun 5, 1981; 1981 Christmas card; 1982 Christmas card
Bertoia, Harry: see Printed Material for autographed exhibition announcement
Blanch, Arnold and Lucile: undated letters (2); Jan 1975; Dec 18, 1975; 1977 Christmas card; Jan 1977; Jan 1978; also see Printed Material for exhibition announcements and catalogs; also see Photographs
Botkin, Henry and Rhoada: undated cards (5); 1973 Christmas card; Jul 29, 1974; Aug 15, 1975; 1975 Christmas card; 1976 Christmas card; 1977 Christmas card; also see Printed Material for an exhibition announcement
Breeskin, Adelyn: May 23, 1969; Dec 19, 1969; Feb 17, 1970; Nov 24, 1970; Jan 14, 1971; Feb 22, 1971; Jul 14, 1971; Sep 13, 1971; Dec 22, 1971; Feb 8, 1972; Mar 30, 1972; May 30, 1972; May 16, 1975; Oct 29, 1975; Nov 21, 1975
Cadmus, Paul: Oct 18, 1956 postcard
Calder, A. Stirling: see Photographs
Castellon, Rolando: undated letter; [Apr 1968]; May 13, 1968; Jan 6, 1972; Apr 5, 1979
Chase, Doris: undated letter
De Creeft, Jose: see Printed Material for an exhibition catalog
Dehn, Virginia (Mrs. Adolph Dehn): undated Christmas card; Dec 9, 1975; [Jan 1976]; Dec 18, 1977; Feb 17, 1978; Dec 16, 1978; Dec 5, 1980; 1981 Christmas card; 1982 Christmas card; also see Printed Material for exhibition announcements and catalogs
Dixon, Constance (“Consie,” daughter of painter of the West, Maynard Dixon): 1949 Christmas card; May 5, 1952; 1961 Christmas card
Engelking, Roberto (architect): undated letter; Jan 16, 1949; Mar 22, 1949
Evergood, Philip: see Printed Material for an exhibition catalog
Ferber, Herbert: see Printed Material for an exhibition catalog
Force, Juliana: [mentioned in Oct 16, 1929, Apr 1930, April 29, 1930, Oct 1, 1930, Oct 25, 1930, Nov 1, 1930, Sep 12, 1932, and Sep 20, 1932 postcards]
Fortess, Karl and Lillian: 1977 Christmas card; Aug 14, 1979; Dec 3, 1979; Jan 8, 1980; 1980 Christmas card; 1981 Christmas card; 1982 Christmas card
Freilich, Michael: undated letter; also see Printed Material for exhibition announcement; also see Photographs
Fruhauf [Vollmer], Aline: undated letters (22); Mar 31, 1944; Jan 3, 1948 (note from Susie Vollmer); Jan 18, 1950; Jan 27, 1950; Apr 15, 1950; Sep 9, 1957; Nov 29, 1957; Jan 15, 1958; Nov 1, 1958; Feb 1, 1961; Dec 21, 1970; Apr 14, 1972; Jan 15, 1974; Jun 12, 1974; Jun 18, 1975; Jun 3, 1977; Oct 23, 1977; 1977 Christmas card; Mar 11, 1978; Jul 18, 1979 (letter from Erwin Vollmer); 1980 Christmas card (from Erwin Vollmer)
Gikow, Ruth: see Printed Material for exhibition announcements
Glassgold, Adolph Cook (painter, former Whitney Museum curator): undated letter; May 26, 1948; 1972 Christmas card; 1977 Christmas card; 1978 New Year's card
Gottlieb, Harry: [postcards dated 1923-1934 mention Gottlieb]; undated letter; Apr 27, 1977; also see Printed Material for an exhibition catalog; also see Photographs
Goulet, Lorrie: see Printed Material for exhibition announcements
Hardy, Marcella (writer from India): May 18, 1956
Hart, Agnes: see Presser, Agnes Hart
Hartwig, Cleo: see Printed Material for an exhibition announcement
Howland, Isabella: undated letter; Sep 19, 1951; 1966 Christmas card; 1967 Christmas card; Jul 17, 1969; Jul 1971; 1971 Christmas card
Klitgaard, Georgina: 1972 Christmas card
Knight, Frederic and Dorothy: undated letters (6); May 19, 1953
Knight, Frederic and Hortense: undated letters (3); Dec 5, 1975; 1977 Christmas card; Nov 18, 1978; Sep 16, 1979; Dec 7, 1980; Nov 23, 1981; also see Printed Material for exhibition announcements and catalogs
Kosloff, Alexis (Russian dancer): [mentioned in Jul 5, 1928 postcard]
Lonergan, Joy (Mrs. John Lonergan): undated letter; Jul 25, 1975; Jul 19, 1977; Apr 27, 1978; Mar 7, 1979; May 25, 1979; Sep 12, 1979; 1981 Christmas card
Marantz, Irving and Evelyn: undated Christmas card; 1971 Christmas card; Jun 4, 1975; 1975 Christmas card; [Sep 5, 1978]; also see Printed Material for an exhibition catalog
Mayer, Ralph and Bena: undated letters (3); Feb 10, 1975; Nov 29, 1977; May 16, 1980; Jan 1, 1981; Aug 7, 1981; 1981 Christmas card
Nakian, Reuben: see Photographs
O'Connor, Francis V.: undated letters (2); Jun 19, 1970; Nov 11, 1970; Dec 22, 1975
Olds, Elizabeth: undated card
Picken, George and Viola: undated letters (3); 1944 Christmas card; 1972 Christmas card; 1974 Christmas card; 1977 Christmas card; also see Printed Material for an exhibition catalog
Pollet, Joseph: see Printed Material for an exhibition catalog; also see Photographs
Presser, Josef and Agnes Hart: undated letters (3); [Sep 1970]; Nov 6, 1973; Feb 25, 1978; Feb 14, 1979; Feb 21, 1979; Mar 4, 1979; Mar 19, 1979; Jun 13, 1979; Sep 7, 1979; [Nov 4, 1979]; also see Printed Material for exhibition announcements and catalogs
Reeves, Ruth: undated letter
Refregier, Anton: 1971 Christmas card; 1973 Christmas card
Robinson, Gertrude (author of The Cardinal, wife of Morton Robinson, novelist and poet): undated letter; Feb 6, 1972; 1974 Christmas card; 1977 Christmas card; Feb 16, 1978; Jun 20, 1978; 1978 Christmas card; Jun 20, 1978; Apr 17, 1979; Sep 10, 1979; Dec 19, 1980; Sep 22, 1981; Oct 17, 1981; Nov 12, 1981
Rockwood, Paul and Alice (painter and Bishop Museum Director): undated letter; Dec 8, 1951; Jan 7, 1960
Rogers, Jane C. (painter, sister of Leon Kroll): undated Christmas card; Dec 30, 1948
Rose, Phyllis (writer): un Christmas card; Jan 23, 1977; Jul 1978; Dec 1981
Sarg, Tony: [mentioned in Oct 30, 1923 and Nov 7, 1923 postcards]
Scaravaglione, Concetta: Dec 22, 1959; Jun 24, 1960; also see Photographs
Shibley, Gertrude (Painter): 1977 Christmas card; Jun 5, 1979
Smith, Gretchen and Mary (daughters of Judson Smith): [Judson Smith mentioned in Feb 17, 1925 postcard]; undated Christmas cards (3); 1977 Christmas card; Sep 16, 1980; see Printed Material for an exhibition catalog for Judson Smith
Soyer, David (son of Moses Soyer): 1977 Christmas card
Soyer, Moses: undated Christmas card
Soyer, Raphael: undated Christmas cards (3); 1980 Christmas card; 1981 Christmas card; 1982 Christmas card; also see Printed Material for exhibition announcements
Still, James (Writer): Nov 8, 1950; Jun 8, 1979
Striebel, Fritzi (Mrs. John Striebel, ceramic sculptor, writer): undated letters (11); Jun 6, 1975; Oct 14, 1975; Feb 1, 1976; [May 1976]; Aug 21, 1976; 1976 Christmas card; 1977 Christmas card; Feb 17, 1979; Apr 11, 1979; Jul 3, 1979; Oct 22, 1979; Nov 6, 1979; Nov 20, 1979; [1979 Christmas card]; Apr 5, 1980; Oct 5, 1980; Dec 30, 1980; Jan 9, 1981; Apr 22, 1981; May 12, 1981; Oct 22, 1981; Nov 16, 1981; 1981 Christmas card; 1982 Christmas card; Feb 26, 1983; [Mar 1983]
Taylor, Joshua: Dec 20, 1972; Dec 5, 1975
Thomson, Virgil (composer): undated letters (2); Apr 1, 1970; Jun 8, 1971; Nov 8, 1971; Jan 1, 1972
Van Veen, Stuyvesant: undated letter; Nov 23, 1976
Varda, Jean: see Photographs
Varian, Dorothy: undated letters (5); Jul 17, 1977; Mar 30, 1981
Vollmer, Aline Fruhauf: see Fruhauf
Whitney Studio Club: [mentioned in Jan 31, 1928, Apr 9, 1928, and Feb 16, 1929 postcards]
Wilder, Thornton: Jul 20, 1953
Wright, Russell (industrial designer): undated Christmas cards (5); Dec 12, 1972; Feb 2, 1976
Yaddo: undated letters (4): Oct 17, 1949; Dec 12, 1949; Jan 9, 1950; Jan 24, 1950; Mar 31, 1950; Aug 23, 1950; Aug 24, 1950; Oct 9, 1950; Oct 11, 1950; Feb 26, 1951; also see Photographs
Zorach, Tessim: May 11, 1968; Nov 20, 1970; Nov 28, 1970
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Names" when they are creators or contributors and under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents.
Subjects:
Calder, Alexander Stirling, 1870-1945; Gottlieb, Harry, 1895-; Nakian, Reuben, 1897-; Pollet, Joseph, 1897-1979; Scaravaglione, Concetta Maria, 1900-1975; Varda, Jean; Art Students League (New York, N.Y.); Federal Art Project (N.Y.); Woodstock Artists Association (Woodstock, N.Y.); Yaddo (Artist's colony)
Subjects-Topical:
Artists' studios -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs; Federal aid to the arts; Artists -- New York (State) -- Woodstock; Sculpture, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York; Women painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Women sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews
Subjects-Geographical:
Woodstock (N.Y.)
Types of Materials:
Christmas cards; Photographs; Prints; Sketchbooks; Sketches
Names:
Baker, Mildred, 1905-; Blanch, Arnold, 1896-1968; Blanch, Lucile, 1895-1981; Breeskin, Adelyn Dohme, 1896-; Dehn, Virginia; Force, Juliana, 1876-1948; Fruhauf, Aline, 1909-1978; Hart, Agnes, 1912-1979; Knight, Frederic C., 1898-1979; Marantz, Irving, 1912-1972; Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1892-1950; Picken, George, 1898-; Presser, Josef, 1907-1967; Refregier, Anton, 1905-; Soyer, Moses, 1899-1974; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987; Thomson, Virgil, 1896-
Provenance
The Eugenie Gershoy papers were donated to the Archives of American Art between 1975 and 1983 by the artist.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels 293, and 4966-4972 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1939-1970, Series 1:; (boxes 1, 9, sol 8, 2 folders)
  Biographical material includes a résumé, membership cards, award certificates, and a biographical sketch. See also sol 8 for oversized biographical material.
  - Biographical material, 1939-1970 (Box 1, Reel 293)
  - Biographical material, 1965-1971 (Box 9 (hol), Reel 293)
- Correspondence, 1914-1983, undated, Series 2:; (boxes 1-6, sol 8, 5.8 linear ft.)
  Correspondence is primarily between Gershoy and family members and colleagues. Correspondence with her sister and brothers and their families discusses Gershoy's activities, including her relationships with Harry Gottlieb and Juliana Force. Correspondence with colleagues includes letters from Elizabeth Ames of Yaddo, Mildred Baker, Arnold and Lucile Blanch, Virginia Dehn, Aline Fruhauf, Agnes Hart, Frederic Knight, Josef Presser, and Virgil Thomson. There are Christmas cards from Irving Marantz, George Picken, Anton Refregier, Moses Soyer, and Raphael Soyer. Correspondence found in box 9 is primarily from museum colleagues including Alfred Barr, Adelyn Breeskin, Juliana Force, and A. Hyatt Mayor. There is also a recommendation from Anton Refregier.
  - Correspondence, first names only, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1, Reel 4966)
  - Correspondence, 1914-1937, (41 folders) (Box 1, Reel 4966)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1945, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 4966)
  - Correspondence, 1946-Mar., 1959, (45 folders) (Box 2, Reel 4967)
  - Correspondence, Apr.-Dec., 1959, (6 folders) (Box 2, Reel 4968)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1970, (48 folders) (Box 3, Reel 4968)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Nov., 1971, (7 folders) (Box 3, Reel 4969)
  - Correspondence, Dec., 1971-Sept., 1974, (29 folders) (Box 4, Reel 4969)
  - Correspondence, Oct., 1974-Feb., 1976, (24 folders) (Box 4, Reel 4970)
  - Correspondence, Mar., 1976-Feb., 1978, (31 folders) (Box 5, Reel 4970)
  - Correspondence, Mar., 1978-Apr., 1979, (19 folders) (Box 5, Reel 4971)
  - Correspondence, May, 1979-1983, (40 folders) (Box 6, Reel 4971)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1971, undated, (10 folders) (Box 9 (hol), Reel 293)
- Business Records, 1952-1978, Series 3:; (box 6, 5 folders)
  Business records include Gershoy's will, receipts for the delivery of artwork to museums, and loan and consignment receipts.
  - Gershoy's will, 1952 (Box 6, Reel 4971)
  - Receipts for delivery of artwork, 1969-1976 (Box 6, Reel 4971)
  - Loan/consignment receipts, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Reel 4971)
  - Miscellaneous receipts, 1967-1978, (2 folders) (Box 6, Reel 4971)
- Notes, 1967-1970, undated, Series 4:; (box 6, 3 folders)
  Notes include lists of names, as well as autographs of Georgia O'Keeffe and Woodstock artists Lucile Blanch, Agnes Hart, Doris Lee, Nicholas Marsicano, Robert Plate, Amy G. Small, Miron Sokole, and Phoebe Towbin.
  - Lists of names, undated (Box 6, Reel 4971)
  - Autographs, 1970, undated (Box 6, Reel 4971)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1967-1968, undated (Box 6, Reel 4971)
- Writings, 1970, undated, Series 5:; (box 6, 2 folders)
  Writings consist of short essays by Gershoy, including “Fantasy and Humor in Sculpture,” instructions on the use of plaster, and a proposed project for a program in ceramics. Writings by others include poems by Bonnie Grainger, a handwritten poem titled "Dirge Without Music" by Edna St. Vincent Millay, and an essay, "On the De-Humanization of Education," by Francis V. O'Connor.
  - Writings by Gershoy, undated (Box 6, Reel 4971)
  - Writings by others, 1970, undated (Box 6, Reel 4971)
- Artwork, 1932-1978, undated, Series 6:; (boxes 6, sol 8, 9, OV 10, 26 folders)
  Art work consists of sketchbooks, drawings, and prints by Gershoy, and art work by others including Alfred Banner, Rosalind Barnett, Lucile Blanch, Petra Cabot, Betty Hamilton, and Florence Weinstein.
  - Sketchbook 1, undated (Box 6, Reel 4971)
  - Sketchbook 2, undated (Box 6, Reel 4971)
  - Sketchbook 3, undated (Box 6, Reel 4971)
  - Sketchbook 4, undated (Box 6, Reel 4972)
  - Sketchbooks 5 and 6, undated (Box 8 (sol), Reel 4972)
  - Sketchbook 7, of Mexico, 1948 (Box 6, Reel 4972)
  - Sketchbook 8, of Mexico, 1971? (Box 6, Reel 4972)
  - Sketchbook 9, of Mexico, 1972 (Box 6, Reel 4972)
  - Sketchbook 10, 1973 (Box 8 (sol), Reel 4972)
  - Drawings by Gershoy (see also sol 8), 1932-1978, undated, (8 folders) (Box 6, Reel 4972)
  - Prints by Gershoy (see also OV 10), 1948, 1975 (Box 8 (sol), Reel 4972)
  - Artwork by others (see also sol 8 for drawings by Rosalind Barnett), 1968-1976, undated, (3 folders) (Box 6, Reel 4972)
  - Artwork, undated, (3 folders) (Box 9 (hol), Reel 293)
  - Artwork, Sketchbooks, 1941, 1949, (2 folders) (Box 9 (hol), Reel 293)
- Printed Material, 1932-1983, undated, Series 7:; (boxes 7 and 9, 19 folders)
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Gershoy and others, press releases, brochures, programs, and reproductions of art work.
  - Clippings, 1952-1983, undated, (5 folders) (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Exhibition announcements and catalogs for Gershoy, 1939-1983, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Exhibition announcements and catalogs for others, 1932-1983, (4 folders) (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Press releases, 1970-1977 (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Brochures, 1966-1979 (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Programs, 1968-1980 (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Reproductions of artwork, greeting cards designed by Gershoy, undated (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Reproductions of artwork by others, undated (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Miscellaneous printed material, 1971-1974 (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Printed material, news clippings, 1940-1970 (Box 9 (hol), Reel 293)
- Photographs, 1916-1983, undated, Series 8:; (boxes 7 and 9, 12 folders)
  Photographs are of Gershoy, her Art Students League class with A. Stirling Calder, her friends, including Harry Gottlieb, Reuben Nakian, Joseph Pollet, Concetta Scaravaglione, Jean Varda, and her friends at Yaddo. There are also photographs of a studio interior, street views of Woodstock, New York, and art work by Gershoy and others.
  - Eugenie Gershoy (with friends), 1916-1983 (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Photographs of Gershoy's friends, 1940-1975, (4 folders) (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Photograph of a studio interior, 1965 (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Photographs of Woodstock, New York, 1982 (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Photographs of artwork by Gershoy, 1970-1972 (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Photographs of artwork by others, 1970-1974 (Box 7 (hol), Reel 4972)
  - Photographs, 1970-1971, undated, (3 folders) (Box 9 (hol), Reel 293)